<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="xdg_splash_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2022 Mark Bolhuis

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="protocol for creating splash surfaces">
    This protocol provides a mechanism for creating splash surfaces.
    A splash surface is typically shown in the center of an output on
    application startup whilst the application is loading.
    A client may use a splash surface to display a simple graphic and/or to
    show application startup progress.

    In order to create a splash surface the user binds to the
    xdg_wm_splash_v1 interface, which, if the compositor supports splash
    surfaces, must be exposed in the global registry. See xdg_wm_splash_v1
    for details on how to create a splash surface.

    If the compositor does not advertise support for splash surfaces the client
    should not use xdg_toplevel as a fallback. A client that does cannot expect
    the compositor to handle the surface appropriately.

    This document adheres to RFC 2119.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
    phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
    corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
    only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
  </description>

  <interface name="xdg_wm_splash_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="create splash surfaces">
      The global interface exposing splash surface functionality.

      This interface provides the get_splash request that a client must use to
      create a splash surface.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the xdg_wm_splash_v1">
        Destroy the xdg_wm_splash_v1 object. This doesn't destroy any splash
        objects.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_splash">
      <description summary="create a new splash surface">
        This creates a splash object for the given xdg_surface and gives the
        associated wl_surface the splash role.

        Creating a splash role for a wl_surface that is already assigned another
        role, or has an attached buffer, is illegal and a protocol error is
        raised.

        See xdg_splash_v1 documentation for further details.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="xdg_splash_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="xdg_surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="xdg_splash_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="splash surface role object">
      This interface defines a xdg_surface role which allows the surface to
      behave like a typical application splash screen.

      The client must commit the associated wl_surface without a buffer attached
      for the splash role to take effect. The compositor must then emit a
      xdg_surface.configure event which the client must respond to using
      xdg_surface.ack_configure. See the xdg_surface documentation for further
      details.

      Once a buffer is attached and committed the compositor should then show
      the user the splash surface in whatever way it sees fit.
      The client must not make any assumptions about how the surface was shown
      to the user.

      A splash role object must be destroyed before its associated xdg_surface.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the splash object">
        This request destroys the role and unmaps the surface.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="configure">
      <description summary="configure the splash surface">
        The configure event may be sent prior to a xdg_surface.configure event
        to communicate the bounds a window geometry size is recommended
        to constrain to.

        The passed max_width and max_height are in surface coordinate space. If
        max_width and max_height are 0, it means bounds is unknown and
        equivalent to as if no configure event was ever sent for this surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="max_width" type="int"/>
      <arg name="max_height" type="int"/>
    </event>

    <event name="close">
      <description summary="close the splash surface">
        A typical splash surface will be closed automatically once the
        application has finished loading, however the compositor may decide
        to close the splash earlier by emitting this event.
        When emitted the client should close the splash surface.

        This event should not be used as an indication to abort application
        startup.
      </description>
    </event>

  </interface>

</protocol>
