<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="ext_ei_session_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2024 Julian Orth

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in
    all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
    OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN
    THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="ext_ei_session_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manager object for creating EI sessions">
      This global allows privileged clients to create EI sessions associated
      with compositor objects.

      Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
      phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
      corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
      only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy this object">
        Destroy this object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="create_output_session">
      <description summary="create an EI session for an output">
        This request creates an EI session using a wl_output as its target.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="ext_ei_session_v1"
           summary="the id of the EI session"/>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output"
           summary="the output to target"/>
    </request>

    <request name="create_toplevel_session">
      <description summary="create an EI session for a toplevel">
        This request creates an EI session using a toplevel as its target.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="ext_ei_session_v1"
           summary="the id of the EI session"/>
      <arg name="toplevel" type="object" interface="ext_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1"
           summary="the toplevel to target"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_ei_session_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="an EI session">
      This object represents an EI session created for a compositor target
      (output or toplevel).
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy this object">
        Destroy this object.

        The compositor will close the EI connection when it receives this event.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="file_descriptor">
      <description summary="the EI session has been established">
        This event is emitted if the EI session was successfully created. The
        file descriptor refers to an EI connection in its initial state. The
        client should set up the connection as usual.

        This event is emitted at most once and is immediately followed by a size
        event.

        The connection will contain exactly one EI region per device. This
        region will refer to the target (output or toplevel) that was used to
        create this session. The client must scale this region to get
        coordinates in compositor space. The scaling can be derived from the
        size event.
      </description>
      <arg name="fd" type="fd"
           summary="the EI file descriptor"/>
    </event>

    <event name="size">
      <description summary="the size of the target in compositor space">
        This event informs the client of the size of the target (output or
        toplevel) in compositor space. It is emitted when the size of the target
        changes.

        Since EI regions are immutable, the client must scale coordinates in EI
        space to map them to compositor space and vice versa. For example, to
        map an x coordinate in EI space to compositor space, the client should
        divide by the width of the EI region and then multiple by the width from
        this event.

        The width and the height are greater than or equal to 0.
      </description>
      <arg name="width" type="int"
           summary="the width of the target"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"
           summary="the height of the target"/>
    </event>

    <event name="stopped">
      <description summary="the EI session has been stopped">
        After this event, this object becomes inert and the client should
        destroy it. If the compositor sent a file descriptor for this session,
        the compositor will close the connection before sending this event.
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
