<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="ext_ei_region_mapper_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2024 Julian Orth

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in
    all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
    OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN
    THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="ext_ei_region_mapper_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="map EI regions to compositor space">
      This global can be used by clients to associate EI mapping ids from
      ei_device.region_mapping_id events with compositor regions.

      Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
      phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
      corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
      only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy this object">
        Destroy this object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="output_region">
      <description summary="create a wl_output association">
        This event associates a wl_output with a region mapping id.

        When this global is initially bound, the compositor emits this event for
        each output global. The client can use wl_display.sync to ensure that it
        has received all events.

        Afterwards, the compositor emits this event when the mapping for an
        output changes or a new output global appears.
      </description>
      <arg name="global_name" type="uint"
           summary="the global name of the wl_output"/>
      <arg name="mapping_id" type="string"
           summary="the EI mapping id"/>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
